<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antisacrilegus: or, A defensative against the plausible pest, or guilded poyson, of that nameless paper, (supposed to be the plot of Dr. C. Burges, and his partners;) which tempts the Kings Majestie by the offer of five hundred thousand pounds, to make good by an Act of Parliament to the purchasers of bishops, deans, and chapters lands, their illegal bargain, for ninety nine years. By John Gauden, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to the Kings most excellent Majesty.</title>
            <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1044_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896313</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896313</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2402:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antisacrilegus: or, A defensative against the plausible pest, or guilded poyson, of that nameless paper, (supposed to be the plot of Dr. C. Burges, and his partners;) which tempts the Kings Majestie by the offer of five hundred thousand pounds, to make good by an Act of Parliament to the purchasers of bishops, deans, and chapters lands, their illegal bargain, for ninety nine years. By John Gauden, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to the Kings most excellent Majesty.</title>
                  <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.B. for Andrew Crook, at the sign of the Green-Dragon in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Burges, Cornelius.  A case concerning the buying of bishops lands.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. 15;".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665. --  Case concerning the buying of bishops lands --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church lands --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Antiſacrilegus: OR, A DEFENSATIVE Againſt the plauſible Peſt, or guilded Poyſon, OF THAT NAMELESS PAPER, (Suppoſed to be the Plot of Dr. <hi>C. Burges,</hi> and his Partners;)</p>
            <p>Which tempts The KINGS MAjESTIE BY THE Offer of Five hundred thouſand pounds, to make good by an Act of Parliament to the Purchaſers of Biſhops, Deans, and Chapters Lands, their illegal bargain, for ninety nine years.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN GA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DEN,</hi> D.D. Chaplain in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.B.</hi> for <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:154159:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154159:2"/>
            <head>ANTISACRILEG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S. OR, A Defenſative againſt the plauſable Peſt, or guilded Poyſon of that nameleſs Paper (ſuppoſed to be the plot of D.<hi>C. Burges</hi> and his unlucky partners which temps the Kings Majeſtie, by the offer of Five hundred thouſand pounds, to make good by an <hi>Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the Purchaſers of Biſhops, Deans, and Chapters Lands, their illegal bargain for ninety nine years.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the Juſtice and Honour of the King be ſuch, as becomes the Son and Succeſſor of ſuch <hi>a Father</hi> (who loved the Church and its juſt Intereſts, more then his own life:) ſo that His Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie will eaſily command ſuch <hi>Satans</hi> to get behinde him, as unworthy of his preſence; whoſe ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious projects and devices deſerve to periſh with their money. Yet that His Excellent Majeſtie and His two Loyal Houſes of Parliament, with all His
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154159:3"/>good Subjects, may ſee the craft of that deſign, and the hook under that bait; it is not amiſs to diſcover the poyſon of ſin and ſhame, of diſhonour and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, of impiety and imprudence wherewith it is fraught, and wherewith it ſeeks to infect the King, the two Houſes of Parliament, and the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, onely to enſure a few unhappy Merchants in their ſacrilegious adventures.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For His Majeſtie to do, as is there unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (becauſe againſt all law and juſtice) deſired, is to be God-father to thoſe ſpurious and illegitimate pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, which were begotten from, and nouriſhed moſt what by tumultuary, diſorderly and violent ways; tending to, and ending ſo much in the ruine of King, Church and State; yea, the very Propoſers do by their bold propoſal clearly confeſs, that they have (yet) no Law or Juſtice for their pretended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes, and conſequently no very good conſciences to keep them, but would gladly by a new price of iniquity, purchaſe to themſelvas a right by Law for ninety nine years, whereas they vapored heretofore as if they had the fee-ſimple; that was (indeed) <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binhoods</hi> pennyworths, at five or ſix years purchaſe, conſidering the timber, houſes and Improvements.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By their inſtancing ſo boldly in the late Kings <hi>forced Conceſsions,</hi> or rather <hi>neceſſitated delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> about granting a Leaſe of improved Church Lands for ninety nine years, in order to redeem His Life, Crown, and poſterity (to which redemption all the Loyal Clergy were more willing to conſent then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154159:3"/>himſelf) theſe Propoſers do dangerouſly inſinuate, as if the preſent King His Son, were in the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of life and fortunes, to which <hi>fraud</hi> and <hi>force</hi> had then reduced His <hi>Royal Father:</hi> Which (bleſſed be God) is not the preſent <hi>caſe</hi> of <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Church;</hi> For the <hi>King</hi> is now <hi>cloathed</hi> with excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and the Church hath put off its <hi>filthy garments, and rags,</hi> wherewith the Enemies of God, the King, and the Church had deformed her. As for His Fathers Murtherers, and the Enemies of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> they are now covered with <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>confuſion of face,</hi> as with <hi>a cloak.</hi> And certainly it is as impudent, as unſeaſonable a deſire, ſince ſome Purchaſers have already <hi>drunk</hi> the <hi>blood,</hi> and eat <hi>the fleſh</hi> of the Kings Father: ſince they have againſt all Law and Conſcience deſtroyed many <hi>Houſes of God,</hi> and <hi>greedily</hi> gaped to devour all Gods porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the <hi>Churches Patrimony;</hi> that the Son now happily reigning in peace, ſhould reward ſuch for their <hi>good works,</hi> by enabling them with an Act of Parliament, to ſtrengthen their now <hi>wambling ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs;</hi> the better to digeſt the Churches Lands and Houſes they have devoured: All which His <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Martyrlie Father</hi> ſought to preſerve as much as His Life, Crown, and Kingdoms; eſteeming all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done to the Church, to be as great reproaches and inſolences againſt His God and Saviour, ſo point blank againſt His Conſcience, as a Chriſtian, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Coronation-Oath</hi> as a King, no leſs then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, by which the Churches rights are ſettled, and ought to be preſerved.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:154159:4"/>
            <p>Thirdly, It would monſtrouſly abate and <hi>eclipſe,</hi> not onely the Renown and Honour of His Majeſtie, who is the Son of ſuch a <hi>Father,</hi> but in time it would ſhrink His <hi>conſtant Revenues;</hi> part of which ariſe from thoſe <hi>Firſt-fruits,</hi> and <hi>yearly Tenths,</hi> which are duly and cheerfully paid by the <hi>Biſhops, Deans</hi> and <hi>Chapters,</hi> out of their Lands and Eſtates, while in their power, and poſſeſſion, and improvement.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This <hi>wretched project</hi> would be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued injury and indignity put upon this <hi>Famous Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and its learned Clergy; who have been formerly eſteemed as eminent, deſerving, and flouriſhing, as any in the world: And all this, meerly upon this account and occaſion, becauſe it hath been for ſome <hi>years</hi> paſt, inſolently ſtripped and abuſed, in which its eminent Biſhops, and other <hi>Divines,</hi> have (like Jewels) been trampled under the feeet <hi>of Swine;</hi> men of ſordid and ſacrilegious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, onely fit to devour and deſtroy <hi>Kings and Biſhops,</hi> things Sacred and Civil.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It would be exceedingly to the diſhonour, not onely of the <hi>Kings Majeſtie,</hi> to degenerate from the examples as of His <hi>many Royal Progenitors,</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who were in all ages <hi>nurſing Fathers</hi> and <hi>Mothers</hi> to this Church, (which God hath put immediately and wholly into their protection, under Chriſt;) and ſpecially, from the incomparable patern of His Father of bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, who expreſſed ſuch holy love, zeal and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the Rites of this Church. But further, it would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154159:4"/>be a moſt uncomely <hi>ſtain</hi> and reproach to the preſent moſt Honourable, Loyal, and Religious <hi>Houſes of Parliament,</hi> both Lords and Commons; whom God hath bleſſed, and eternally honoured, in making them the happy Repairers of our Civil and Deſperate breaches: How can they then with any honour or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſacrifice the Church any longer to theſe <hi>Apollyons</hi> and <hi>Abaddons;</hi> its ſacrilegious Waſters and Opppreſſors.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, This deſign of the <hi>Purchaſees,</hi> if obtained, would ſo cruelly weaken, peel, barkround, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt the plenty, honour, power and authority of this Church, and its Clergie, both as Chriſtian, and reformed, in all its ancient <hi>Rights, Immunities</hi> and <hi>Enjoyments</hi> (which are as well ſettled by Laws anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and modern, as any civil eſtates are, or can be) that it would never recover its beauty and flouriſhing luſtre, of late ſo much deflored; but both <hi>Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and all <hi>ſober Reformation,</hi> would daily decay and wither, by ſucceſſive attempts of ſacriledge and ſchiſm, till all were run to <hi>Prophaneneſs, Atheiſm, Anarchy,</hi> and <hi>Barbarity;</hi> which ever follow as the idleneſs and luxury, ſo the deſpicable <hi>poverty</hi> and <hi>tenuity</hi> of Church-men; of vvhich <hi>Greece</hi> of old, <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> of late, and <hi>England</hi> laſt of all are evident, but ſad experiments.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If ſuch an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould paſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and againſt the conſent of the Clergy (who are by Law the <hi>Proprieters</hi> and enjoyers of thoſe eſtates, <hi>under God</hi> and <hi>the King</hi>) which conſent is never like
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154159:5"/>to be gained, as it cannot reaſonably be asked:) It would make, not onely the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> but in, and with them, the <hi>whole Nation,</hi> ſhrewdly ſuſpected, if not actually <hi>guilty</hi> of that <hi>enormous ſin</hi> and <hi>curſe of Sacriledge;</hi> which even Dr. <hi>Burges</hi> owns to be ſuch, though not in the caſe of Biſhops and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Lands, becauſe it is his <hi>own caſe</hi> and great <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</hi> Let him but have his bargain, with <hi>Judas,</hi> he cares not whom he betrays, or what truth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he ſells; though it come up to a moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent robbing of God, his Miniſters, the whole Church, its reverend <hi>Fathers,</hi> and moſt <hi>eminent Sons,</hi> yea, the whole body and fraternity of the <hi>Faithful</hi> in the Land, of that <hi>double honour,</hi> both for maintenance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, which agreeably to the vvord of God <hi>allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, accepting,</hi> or <hi>commanding</hi> ſuch grateful and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary retributions of their temporals, to thoſe that impart things ſpiritual, hath been <hi>freely given,</hi> piouſly devoted, and by the Lavvs of the Land oft confirm'd as ſacred and inviolable to the Church and Clergy, in order to promote the Worſhip and <hi>glory of God,</hi> vvith the good of <hi>ſouls,</hi> by the order, peace, plenty, honor, government and authority of the Church, and its Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, both governing, and governed. The poor man Dr. <hi>Burges</hi> cryes out like <hi>Steutor,</hi> of the gnats of his ovvn private injuries, ſuffered from the <hi>Corporation of Wells</hi> in his <hi>Biſhops Lands;</hi> yet he can ſvvallovv the camel of <hi>his own great purchaſe</hi> of them, though vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Lavv to enable him; or any conſent of the Biſhop or others by Lavv inveſted in them; nay ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a <hi>canine appetite,</hi> he is not yet <hi>ſick</hi> of <hi>the ſin,</hi> but onely afraid to <hi>vomit</hi> up thoſe <hi>ſacred morſels,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154159:5"/>would fain have a <hi>retentive cordial</hi> from the <hi>King, and two Houſes;</hi> who have hitherto, and in them the whole <hi>Nation</hi>) been by a <hi>ſpecial providence</hi> kept from that <hi>ſin and ſhame;</hi> For what ever in this <hi>kind of chaffering</hi> hath hitherto been done in <hi>England,</hi> during our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, was but the counſel and practice of ſome few men, without and againſt all Laws of God and the Land, which teach all honeſt men to abhor <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> as <hi>Idolatry;</hi> as a ſin of the firſt magnitude againſt every precept of the <hi>firſt Table;</hi> condemned in all ages by all men <hi>morally juſt,</hi> as being againſt the light of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and natural Religion, to <hi>rob God:</hi> Therefore deteſted always by <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Greeks</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians,</hi> by <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Mahometans,</hi> by all <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as not to be diſpenſed withall, but in a caſe of <hi>higher charity</hi> and neceſſity, for Gods glory and the Churches good; and this with unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned purpoſe of making, when able, full reſtitution, in kind, or in ſomething equivalent. Which <hi>Juſtice</hi> is aſſerted by the Old and New Teſtament, by the Laws of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and of all Empires antient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern; by the <hi>Canons</hi> of all Churches, by all <hi>Councils, Fathers, Church-Hiſtorians,</hi> and <hi>learned Divines</hi> on all ſides (as Dr. <hi>Burges</hi> is forced to confeſs) being a moſt impudent and deteſtable ſin, never to be palliated or excuſed, ſeldom or never pardoned or repented of; becauſe it abhors any <hi>reſtitution;</hi> as we ſee in Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> his <hi>terrors</hi> and <hi>clamors;</hi> but is uſually puniſhed with <hi>hardneſs of heart;</hi> and <hi>ſearedneſs of conſcience</hi> in private perſons, ever fatal and unproſperous to Prince and people, juſtly revenged by God and man to many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, by laſting and unexpiable curſes; to which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154159:6"/>the King, Parliament and Nation ought not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon any terms.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Thus to <hi>peel</hi> and <hi>pillage</hi> the Church and Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> after ſo many and long <hi>exhauſtings</hi> will give joy and ſatisfaction to none but the enemies of the King, the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation:</hi> Either the envious <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or the covetous and cruel <hi>Fanaticks;</hi> who are as the <hi>locuſts, caterpillers &amp; palmerworms</hi> of this <hi>Church;</hi> the one hoping to devour what the other leaves: Nor is there any reaſon that the beſt and moſt of the Nation rich and poor ſhould be all injured, ſcandalized and robbed by the Church and Clergies diminution and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, only to gratifie a few <hi>unreaſonable</hi> and <hi>undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Purchaſers</hi> of <hi>Church lands;</hi> who are neither good to the Tenants; nor to the poor, nor to their Prince, nor to their Saviour.</p>
            <p>Ninethly, This <hi>alienation</hi> and long <hi>diverſion</hi> of the Churches revenues, will much diſcourage all <hi>learned induſtry</hi> and <hi>proficiency in this Nation;</hi> it will damp the the ſpirits and ſtudies of both our famous <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> which now begin to flouriſh again. It will debaſe and <hi>cripple</hi> the dignity and authority of this Church and the Clergy, both <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> who of old did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great and good works: It will much defeat his Majeſties charitable deſign and <hi>declared pleaſure</hi> for augmenting <hi>Vicaridges</hi> out of Church <hi>Impropriations;</hi> It will obſtruct and dry up the ſtream of <hi>charity</hi> and <hi>hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality,</hi> which ſhould be moſt exemplary in the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; and it will only make way for <hi>avarice, ignorance, anarchy</hi> and <hi>confuſion</hi> in the Church, which cannot but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154159:6"/>endanger the peace and ſafety of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as of late we have ſeen to our woe.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, To anſwer the temptation of preſent gain, which as the <hi>devil to Chriſt</hi> in the wilderneſs, that <hi>ſerpentine paper</hi> offers to his Excellent Majeſty, as if the liberal and loyal purchaſers would advance 50000 <hi>l.</hi> for his <hi>Majeſties ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a <hi>goodly ſum</hi> indeed, if it came out of their own eſtates and purſes, which it doth not; but it is too ſinall a ſum to engage any honeſt man upon ſo <hi>great a ſin as Sacriledge;</hi> to which all the worlds gain will not tempt a King, or any true Chriſtian, who knows how to value his ſoul or the Church of Chriſt, or Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or his Kingdoms and conſciences peace, or his own and the Nations honor, or his Clergies merit and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Majeſty deſerves and enjoys ſo much of the <hi>hearts and loves</hi> of his people, that he needs not fear any vvant: nor vvill he be ever driven to make uſe of ſuch <hi>crafty Merchants,</hi> or to partake of their filthy lucre, who vvould fain dravv the King to be their part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and to <hi>crown their Sacrilegious projects</hi> with his <hi>Princely Diadem;</hi> and while to ſave the <hi>common people of the Nation a few pounds,</hi> His Majeſty ſhould contract upon his Throne and Kingdom, his Conſcience and People the <hi>ſin and ſhame of Sacriledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Experience tells us (which Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> obſerves) that as no private Families, ſo nor any Kings, ever grew <hi>more comfortably rich,</hi> or <hi>laſtingly proſperous</hi> by any <hi>Sacrilegious practices;</hi> from the <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154159:7"/>of which</hi> all ſevere <hi>conſciences</hi> ſhould abſtain, being to the reproach and injury, not onely of the Clergy, who are amongſt the beſt of Subjects; but even of God the giver of all, and Chriſt Jeſus the the meriter of all we have, or can give to God and his Church; yea it tends to the indignity of the whole Engliſh Nation, heretofore ſo <hi>generous, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificient</hi> and <hi>reſpectful</hi> to its reverend <hi>Biſhops</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as to entertain and treat them worthy of their <hi>holy labors</hi> and <hi>high profeſſion,</hi> to encourage their <hi>Piety, Hoſpitality</hi> and <hi>Charitie,</hi> with <hi>plenty,</hi> yea <hi>with an honorable ſuperfluity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. As His Majeſty by this <hi>fallacious bargain</hi> ſhall diminiſh his conſtant Revenue, which is retributed to the <hi>Crown from the Clergie,</hi> in <hi>Firſt-fruits</hi> and <hi>Tenths;</hi> ſo he will loſe thoſe <hi>grateful</hi> and <hi>liberal Subſidies, Aids</hi> and <hi>Fifteens</hi> which the Clergy were wont frequently to preſent with <hi>thanks</hi> and <hi>chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> to the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> as their moſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Benefactors and Protectors; which will in leſs then a quarter of Ninety nine years, amount to far more then that ſum which thoſe <hi>Sophiſters</hi> and <hi>Huck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> do offer, if the Church and Clergy be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that opulency and freedom with which they are endowed by God, and good Princes bounty.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ſtately <hi>Fabricks of Cathredral Churches</hi> beſides the <hi>Biſhops, Deans</hi> and <hi>Chapters</hi> houſes, which were once the glory of our Nation, of our Cities and our Church, being now ſorely demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and barbarouſly vvaſted, vvill never be repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154159:7"/>but run to irrecoverable ruines, if the Clergy be novv deprived of improving the Church lands or if they be curtailed by ſuch an <hi>alienation</hi> or <hi>leaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of them for Ninety nine years: All vvhich re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations by the preſent advance of the Churches Revenues in Clergy-mens hands, may by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties gracious <hi>care and command</hi> be timely ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ected.</p>
            <p n="6">6. All this <hi>(Ampullae)</hi> or ſpecious offer of Five hundred thouſand pounds, as it is in truth not one penny out of the Purchaſers own <hi>Patrimony</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eſtate,</hi> ſo it is not at all in favour of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, but of themſelves; who having taſted how <hi>ſweet and improveable</hi> the <hi>Churches Lands</hi> are, do deſire to have their great <hi>penniworths</hi> made good to them, which in a moral ſenſe is impoſſible, unleſs <hi>God</hi> and <hi>all parties concerned</hi> do conſent. As for their care of his Majeſties <hi>ſupplies,</hi> it is certain the greateſt <hi>Enemies</hi> to the Church, are no <hi>Friends</hi> to His Majeſty: Nor is it without great regret that the <hi>Crown Lands</hi> are now redeemed out of ſome of their jaws, who have good <hi>ſtomachs</hi> to both, if they had but the <hi>retentive Faculty,</hi> and had ſome <hi>Peptick powder:</hi> But if theſe <hi>Projectors</hi> have ſuch a zeal to His Majeſty, let them preſent him with ſome thing that was and is their own; or at leaſt with the profits they have made of the purchaſes of <hi>Church Lands and Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. As it will be infinitely more to his <hi>Majeſties</hi> comfort, honor and happineſs, <hi>to render to God the things that are Gods,</hi> who hath by miraculous mercies
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154159:8"/>rendred to him the things that are his, as our <hi>Coeſar</hi> and rightful <hi>Soveragine:</hi> ſo the Godly Biſhops and other dignified Clergy men, who are or ſhall be intruſted by his Majeſties Grant and Seal in their reſpective eſtates and rights, by Law due to the Church, theſe (no doubt) will hold themſelves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſo obliged to his gracious Majeſty, as the great Patron and Reſtorer of the Church and Clergy, that they will ſtudy in all wayes of piety to God, and Loyalty to his Majeſty, to expreſs their gratitude in ſuch ſort as ſhall be moſt becomming their duty, and moſt acceptable to his Majeſty. And certainely one pound thus retributed to his Majeſty by the Clergy, as is the rightful owners and poſſeſſors of thoſe Eſtates, will thrive better and do his Majeſty more good with their prayers, then ten thouſands taken from them, or pretended to be given to his Majeſty by others, who have been, and deſire ſtill to be the Purchaſers and improvers of the Church Lands and revenues to their own, not to the Kings or Churches benefit, whoſe Sacrilegious depredations, acquiſitions and oblations can expect no bleſſing from God, or men, on giver or receiver.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To conclude, That the <hi>Reverend Biſhops,</hi> and others <hi>of the Clergie</hi> who are concerned in theſe Lands, may not ſeem leſs <hi>equanimous</hi> and <hi>condeſcending,</hi> by all meet ways, to the quiet of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> It is not to be doubted but they will upon ſuch <hi>reaſonable termes</hi> (as his Majeſty and all perſons of reaſon and honor ſhall approve) make ſuch <hi>agreements</hi> with theſe pretended <hi>Purchaſers,</hi> or rather <hi>Morgagees</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154159:8"/>Church Lands as are under any <hi>Capacity</hi> or Loyal merit of a fair <hi>compoſition,</hi> that whatſoever they are out of purſe upon a due <hi>accompt,</hi> they may have <hi>reimburſed</hi> either in monies or in ſuch equivalency of <hi>Leaſe</hi> and <hi>Tennancy,</hi> as the Clergy are by Law enabled to make.</p>
            <p>And however in ſo notorious a caſe as this was (where the known laws of God and man were moſt evident) there was, <hi>Caveat Emptor</hi> written in great Letters, that is ſufficient <hi>caution</hi> or <hi>warning</hi> given to every wiſe and honeſt man, to take heed of ſuch <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious ſales, purchaſes</hi> (which can no more be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in reaſon, law or conſcience) becauſe the office <hi>of Biſhops</hi> and uſe of <hi>Deanes</hi> and <hi>Chapters,</hi> were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and againſt law taken away, (as the <hi>learned</hi> Dr. <hi>Burges</hi> accutely pleads in his <hi>caſe</hi>) than <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> could juſtify the taking poſſeſſion of <hi>Naboths</hi> Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard becauſe he was now killed) yet becauſe the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion</hi> was ſtrong as well as the <hi>temptation,</hi> and many now Loyal Subjects, might poſſibly in the <hi>ſimplicity of their ſouls</hi> be engaged in ſuch unjuſt <hi>bargains,</hi> care may be had that they ſhall ſuſtaine no loſs, though they get no <hi>great gain,</hi> which equability will ſatisfie all ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded men.</p>
            <p>As for others, whoſe gain is their God, whoſe <hi>apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy</hi> hath made them deſperate Enemies to the Church and Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe covetous and contentious ambition is a bottomleſs &amp; unſatiable gulph of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, aiming in their deſpair and hypocriſie, to ſwallow up or imbroyl a new both Church and State, King and Clergy all things ſacred and civil, if they had power
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154159:9"/>equal to their rage, deſpite and malice. Theſe mens <hi>propoſals</hi> and <hi>clamors</hi> are not to be regarded by pious honeſt and reſolute men, farther then to be conſtantly denied and ſeverely ſuppreſſed; Notwithſtanding that they be as importune as Dr. <hi>Burges himſelf</hi> who with his Diurnal <hi>Libells</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets</hi> runs to the City of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Wells, grining</hi> and <hi>grudging,</hi> that he is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with his beloved purchaſes of Church Lands, as he well deſerves, being a perſon of that repute and worth, that beſides other old and new reports of his vertues, he is by a decree in <hi>Chancery May,</hi> 1. 1657. adorned with this <hi>Elogy</hi> upon record; <hi>As an Author</hi> and <hi>proſecutor</hi> of ſo <hi>great injuſtice</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion, as are utterly unbecomming a man of common honeſty,</hi> much <hi>more a Miniſter of the Goſpel,</hi> whoſe converſation ſhould be an example (as the decree ſpeaks) of piety and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to others.</p>
            <p>If this Belwether be ſuch a <hi>Cretian</hi> and Borborites, who was the gracious Author of that infamous Libel, called the <hi>Anatomy,</hi> being the <hi>Epitomy</hi> of Dr. <hi>Burges</hi> his <hi>falſity, folly,</hi> and <hi>ſcurrility,</hi> not worth a ſober mans <hi>anſwering</hi> or <hi>reading;</hi> what ſhall we think of the reſt of that <hi>heard,</hi> which of latter years have been <hi>fatted</hi> with the Church Lands and the eſtates of other men, much <hi>theirs,</hi> and his <hi>betters,</hi> who never needed any <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgators</hi> for their innocency and credit? In whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half that <hi>Boanerges</hi> or great <hi>zealot</hi> for the <hi>reforming</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> (in order to keep his <hi>Biſhops Lands</hi> by keeping out the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Bathe</hi> and <hi>Wels</hi> and all others, of that Cathedral, from repoſſeſſing their own eſtates) hath for ſo oft filled and killed the world
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154159:9"/>with the poyſonous <hi>cramb</hi> of his <hi>Paradoxes;</hi> That <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> (in all mens ſence but his own is <hi>no ſin;</hi> And that the ſelling and buying of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Cathedrals Lands, is no <hi>ſacrilege,</hi> But this <hi>Mountebankry</hi> is now grown ſtale and ſcorned even by the vulgar; nor will it ſerve to keep him from the Juſtice of Gods and mans Laws, which require reſtitution of his own fine new Houſes and Gardens in liew of of theſe good old houſes of the <hi>Biſhops, Deans,</hi> and others which that <hi>dilapidetor</hi> of the Church hath pulled down.</p>
            <p>Nor will it ſerve his turn, to cry out that his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſo ſore grieved with the collick of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that he cannot indure the return of <hi>Biſhops, Deans,</hi> and <hi>Chapters:</hi> Indeed his fits and gripes ariſe from the juſt fear he hath, that theſe his rivals may now drive him out of the <hi>Babel</hi> which he hath built, and diſpoſſeſs him of his unlucky Purchaſes, which to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by any meanes this <hi>Proteus</hi> will rather diſguiſe himſelf into <hi>Presbytery</hi> and <hi>Independency,</hi> contrary to his former hue and profeſſion, then return to a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtituted Epiſcopacy which is (certainly) more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant by far with the law of the Land, and the genius of the people of England, then either of the other pittiful novelties and much more agreeable to his ſo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Covenant, ſince in that he expreſly engaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not onely againſt his ſo feared Prelacy and Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but alſo againſt Schiſme and Superſtition; of both which thoſe ſeditious innovations in Church and State, are as vehemently ſuſpected and charged by learned and godly men, as <hi>Gehazy</hi> was with <hi>Naamans Leproſie,</hi> when having ſtolen his <hi>undeſerved fees</hi> for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154159:10"/>his Maſters miracle, he went out of <hi>Eliſhas</hi> preſence, as white as <hi>ſnow:</hi> which bleſſing may in a few years, more befall this Black-defender, that <hi>Sacriledge</hi> (that is ſelling of Church Lands againſt law) <hi>is no ſin;</hi> Whom all ſober minded men will leave to be puniſhed with his own manners; yet ſo as to follow his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable ſoul, with ſuch prayers as Chriſtian Charity will permit, for thoſe that have not ſinned the ſin unto death, by willful and known apoſtacy; and by oppoſing of moſt evident truths, ſuch as theſe are, that God and his Church are not to be rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:154159:10"/>
            <head>Books written by Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> and ſold by <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> at the green Dragon in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>HIeraſpiſtes,</hi> A Defence for the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Three Sermons preached on publick occaſions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Funerals</hi> made <hi>Cordials,</hi> in a Sermon preached at the Interment of the Corps of <hi>Robert Rich,</hi> Heir apparent to the Earldom of <hi>Warwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. A ſermon preached at the Funeral of Dr. <hi>Ralph Broun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter</hi> (<hi>Decemb.</hi> 17. 1659.) with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his <hi>Life and Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A <hi>Petitionary Remonſtrance</hi> in the behalf of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Miniſters and Scholars.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſive Medicaſtri,</hi> Slight healers of publique hurts, ſet forth in a Sermon Preached in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, <hi>London,</hi> before the right honorable Lord Mayor, Lord General, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, Common-Council, &amp; Companies of the honorable City of <hi>London, Febr.</hi> 28. 1659. being a day of Solemn thanksgiving unto God, for reſtoring the Secluded Members of Parliament to the houſe of Commons, (And for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the City) as a Door of Hope thereby opened to the fulneſs and freedom of future Parliaments: The moſt probable means under God for healing the Hurts, and recovering the health of theſe three Brittiſh King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Gods great Demonſtrations and Demands of Juſtice, Mercy and Humility, ſet forth in a Sermon preached before the Honorable Houſe of Commons, at their Solema Faſt, before their firſt ſitting, <hi>April</hi> 30. 1660.</p>
            <p>ΑΝΑΛΥΣΙΣ, The looſing of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Bands; ſetting forth the true ſenſe and ſolution of the Covenant in point of Conſcience, ſo far as it relates to the Government of the Church by Epiſcopacy.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
